到目前为止我们看过的机器人在2D平面上移动但是大多数有用的机器人都移动了
The robots that we looked at so far move in the 2D plane but most useful robots move in
三个维度。我们现在要做的是确定末端执行器的姿势
three dimensions. What we want to do now is to determine the pose of the end effector
这个机器人在三维空间中移动。我们遵循的过程非常非常
of this robot which moves in three dimensional space. The process we follow is very, very
类似于我们为二维机器人所做的过程。首先我们介绍一下
similar to the process we did for the two dimensional robots. First of all we introduced
参考坐标系然后我们指示机器人的姿势对象的部分
a reference coordinate frame and then we indicate the part of the robot the object whose pose
我们感兴趣的是，这是机器人的末端执行器，用符号ksiE表示。
we’re interested in, that’s the end effector of the robot indicated here by the symbol ksi E.
然后，第一步是围绕z轴旋转坐标系一个量Q1。然后
The first step then is a rotation of the coordinate frame about the z axis by an amount Q1. Then
我们在x方向上将该坐标系转换为A1的长度
we translate that coordinate frame in the x direction by an amount A1 the length of
第一个链接。然后我们再次围绕z轴旋转坐标系Q2。
the first link. Then we rotate the coordinate frame about the z axis again by an amount Q2.
接下来，我们在X方向上转换A2，即第二个的长度
Next we translate in the X direction by an amount A2 that’s the length of the second
链接。然后我们再次围绕Z轴旋转角度Q3，最后我们翻译
link. Then we rotate around the Z axis again by the angle Q3 and finally we translate in
Z方向的量为Q4。
the Z direction by the amount Q4.
我们现在已经将机器人末端执行器的姿势描述为链，一系列基本的
We now have described the pose of the robot’s end effector as a chain, a sequence of elementary
齐次变换矩阵。所有矩阵都属于集合SE3
homogeneous transformation matrices. All of the matrices belong to the set SE3 that’s
三维空间中所有旋转和平移的集合。我们可以扩大
the set of all rotations and translations in three dimensional space. We could expand
将每个基本矩阵中的每个矩阵相乘并将它们相乘以得出
out each of these elementary matrices and multiply them all together to come up with
一个单一的同质转换度量表示姿势的最终效应器
a single homogeneous transformation metric representation the pose the end effector of
这个Scara机器人。这个小机器人已经四个自由度，四个旋转关节。
this Scara robot. This small robot has gone four degrees of freedom, four rotational joints.
所以第一次旋转是围绕这样的轴。你看到整个手臂都在转动
So the first rotation is around an axis like this. You see that the whole arm rotates around
基地。第二个旋转关节有一个像这样的轴，我们可以说是
the base. The second rotating joint has got an axis like this and we can say that the
整个臂可以绕这个轴旋转。第三个关节绕该轴旋转，
whole arm can rotate around this axis here. The third joint is rotation around this axis,
你看到长臂绕着它旋转而第四个关节是一个旋转
you see that longer arm rotates around that and the fourth joint is a rotation around
这里有一个轴。您可以看到整组机构相对于下臂旋转。
an axis here. You can see that the whole group of mechanism rotates with respect to the lower arm.
让我们看看这四个联合教育机器人吧。我们有一个相当的
Let’s finish off by looking at this four joint educational robot. We've had quite a
现在我们应该能够写下机器人的表达式
bit of practice by now that we should be able to write down the expression for the robot
末端效应器几乎通过检查。
end effector pose almost by inspection.
所以这就是我思考这个问题的方式。我想机器人已经拉长了
So this is the way I think about the problem. I imagine that the robot is stretched down
垂直，两根手指指向天空，然后我写下序列
vertically with its two fingers pointing to the sky and then I just write down the sequence
变形首先，机器人绕参考Z轴旋转
of transformations. First of all the robots rotates around the reference Z axis by the
量Q1然后我们向上移动一点，这是在Z方向，然后我们旋转
amount Q1 and then we move up a little bit which is in the Z direction and then we rotate
围绕Y轴的量为Q2。
around the Y axis by the amount Q2.
然后我们向上移动一点，然后遇到下一个关节，我们绕着旋转的关节3
Then we move up a little bit and encounter the next joint, joint 3 we rotate around the
Y轴的量Q3然后我们在Z方向上向上移动了一点点
Y axis by the amount Q3 then we move up a bit more in the Z direction encounter the
最后一个关节，关节4我们围绕Y轴旋转关节角度Q4。然后我们搬家
last joint, joint 4 we rotate around the Y axis by the joint angle Q4. And then we move
在Z方向上向上一点，直到我们到达手指的尖端。
up a bit more in the Z direction until we reach the tip of the fingers.
因此，只需通过联合，精神上通过机器人机制联合，我们链接
So just by mentally walking through the robot mechanism joint by joint, link by link we
可以写下末端效应器姿势的表达式。然后这很简单
can write down an expression for the pose of the end effector. Then it’s a simple
扩展矩阵然后将它们相乘的问题。和我们
a matter of expanding out the matrices and then multiplying them all together. And we
可以使用像MATLAB这样的工具让我们很容易。
can use a tool like MATLAB to make that very easy for us.
现在我们将使用MATLAB来确定该机器人的末端执行器的姿势
Now we’re going to use MATLAB to determine the pose of the end effector of this robot
它以三维方式移动，我们将以象征性的方式进行，但首先是
which moves in three dimensions and we’re going to do this symbolically but first of
我将为各种链接长度A1，A2，A3和定义一些符号变量
all I’m going to define some symbolic variables for the various link lengths A1, A2, A3, and
A4以及四个关节角度Q1，Q2，Q3和Q4。我们将使用trchain
A4 and also for the four joint angles Q1, Q2, Q3 and Q4. We’re going to use the trchain
功能再次。这次我们将使用名为trchain的函数进行操作
function again. This time we’re going to use the function called trchain which operates
在三个维度而不是在二维操作的函数trchain2
in three dimensions rather than the function trchain2 which operates in two dimensions
我们在前面的例子中使用过的。
that we used in the previous examples.
现在我开始编写这个变换字符串，这样我们就可以围绕它进行旋转了
And now I start to write this transform string so we’re going to do a rotation around the
Z轴由Q1然后我们将在A1方向进行Z方向的平移
Z axis by Q1 and then we’re going to do a translation in the Z direction by A1 then
我们将在第二季度围绕Y轴进行旋转，然后我们将会这样做
we’re going to do a rotation around the Y axis by Q2 and then we’re going to do
A2的另一个Z方向平移，然后我们将轮换
another translation in the Z direction by A2 and then we’re going to do a rotation
在Q3附近围绕Y轴然后我们将在Z方向上进行另一次平移
around the Y axis by Q3 and then we’re going to do another translation in the Z direction
通过A3然后我们将在Q4绕Y轴旋转，最后进行平移
by A3 and then we’re going to do a rotation around the Y axis by Q4 and finally a translation
在A4方向的Z方向。
in the Z direction by A4.
我关闭了那根弦，现在我传递了关节角度Q1，Q2，Q3和Q4，在这里我们
I close that string and now I pass in the joint angles Q1, Q2, Q3 and Q4 and here we
具有表示该机器人姿态的均匀变换的表达式
have the expression for the homogeneous transformation which represents the pose of this robot which
三维移动。因为机器人的三维操作是均匀的
moves in three dimensions. Because the robot’s operating in three dimensions this homogeneous
变换是一个四乘四的矩阵。我们可以看到它非常庞大而复杂
transformation is a four-by-four matrix. And we can see that it’s quite a large and complex
表达式，我需要横向滚动很多才能结束它。
expression and I need to scroll sideways quite a lot to get to end of it.
如果我想确定这个机器人的末端执行器的X坐标，我会的
If I wanted to determine the X coordinate of the end effector of this robot I would
通过获取此同类的第一行和第四列中的元素来做到这一点
do that by taking the element in the first row and the forth column of this homogeneous
转换矩阵，这将是该机器人的X坐标的表达式
transformation matrix and that would be the expression for the X coordinate of this robot
而且这本身就是一个非常复杂的表达。
and again that itself is quite a complex expression.